اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ۞
بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۞
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرا
The next important event is the marriage of Rasool Allah ﷺ to Khadijah(خديجه).
Khadijah(خديجه) was a well known and prosperous woman in Makkah, she was wealthy,
she wasn't married, she was older in age.
And she used to hire men to travel for her and do business.
Because you know that
the trade of the people of Makkah used to be based on traveling to Yemen and Syria, Ash-sham(الشام).
Allahسبحانه وتعالى describes that, in Surah(سورة) Quraish(قُرَيْشْ):
لِإِيلَافِ قُرَيْشٍ۝إِيلَافِهِمْ رِحْلَةَ الشِّتَاءِ وَالصَّيْفِ۝
فَلْيَعْبُدُوا رَبَّ هَٰذَا الْبَيْتِ۝الَّذِي أَطْعَمَهُمْ مِنْ جُوعٍ وَآمَنَهُمْ مِنْ خَوْفٍ۝
They had the journey of winter and the journey of summer,
one to Yemen and one to Ash-Sham(الشام).
So, Khadijah(خديجه) would hire men to work for her and take care of her business.
She happened to hire Muhammadﷺ, she heard about his honesty,
she was running into trouble with a lot of men not being honest.
So, she wanted to hire somebody who was trustworthy.
She heard about Muhammadﷺ, so she hired him,
and she had her servant accompany Muhammadﷺ.
Her servant's name is Mesarah(ميسرا),
Muhammadﷺ  went to Ash-Sham(الشام) did business for her, came back.
Mesarah(ميسرا) reported back to his master.
Mesarah(ميسرا) went to Khadijah(خديجه) and told her:
This man, his trustworthiness and honesty is amazing, it's outstanding,
and he was praising Muhammadﷺ.
Well, Khadijah(خديجه) became very interested in Muhammadﷺ
I mean, his character was admirable.
Khadijah رضي الله عنها, who was a wealthy woman,
who was sought after by the noble men of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
she said: I want to marry you,
and Rasool Allah ﷺ agreed.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was 25 and she was 40,
the difference was 15 years.
She was his senior and Rasool Allah ﷺ never married anyone else
before Khadijah رضي الله عنها passed away.
All of the surviving children of Rasool Allah ﷺ were from Khadijah(خديجه),
Fatimah(فاطمه) was the daughter of Khadijah رضي الله عنها.
She bore six children for him.
Zainab(زينب), Ruqaiyah(رقيّه), Umm Kalsoom(ام كلثوم), Fatimah(فاطمه),
Al-Qasim(القاسم) and Abdullah(عبدالله).
And none of them ended up having descendants except Fatimah رضي الله عنها.
And that is where the lineage of Rasool Allah ﷺ is continuing
through the descendants of Fatimah(فاطمه) and Ali(علي).
Rasool Allah ﷺ loved her so much, and Rasool Allah ﷺ kept his loyalty to Khadijah(خديجه), even after she passed away,
he would always remember her, always mention her name
and that sometimes would cause jealousy among the other wives of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
But Rasool Allah ﷺ had so much love and admiration to Khadijah(خديجه) and so much respect for her
because Khadijah(خديجه) is the one, who stood up for him and supported him,
when everybody else betrayed Muhammadﷺ.
Ayesha رضي الله عنها, who was the most beloved to Rasool Allah ﷺ, after that, she would sometimes feel this jealousy.
In Bukhari(بخاريْ) and Muslim(مسلم), it says that
Ayesha(عائشه) said:
I did not become jealous of any of the wives of the Prophet صلى الله عليه وسلم except Khadijah(خديجه)
and I have not seen her.
The Messenger of Allah used to, at times slaughter a sheep and say
send it to the Friends of Khadijah(خديجه).
So, not only did Rasool Allah ﷺ always remember her,
he kept on maintaining a relationship with the friends of Khadijah(خديجه).
And one day I angered him,
when he said that
by replying out to jealousy, Khadijah(خديجه),
so he ﷺ said: I have been given by Allah her love.
Once he mentioned the name of Khadijah(خديجه), so Ayesha(عائشه) was upset.
Rasool Allah ﷺ responded and said: This is something from Allah, I was given her love.
It's not something that I control, Allah has put her love in my heart.
In another Hadith(حديث) narrated by Ahmad(احمد) and Tirimdhi(ترمذي), Ayesha رضي الله عنها said:
The Messenger of Allah used to, many times not leave his home without praising Khadijah(خديجه),
I mean, this is amazing.
How much love Rasool Allah ﷺ had for her.
One of the days he praised her and out of jealousy, I said:
Was she not but an elder woman that Allah has replaced her for you, with what is better?
He became angered and said: No, by Allah, He did not replace me with anyone better.
For she had faith in me, when the people rejected,
she believed me, when the people belied me,
she made comfortable with what she had, when the people denied me,
and Allah has blessed me with children from her.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ would become angry,
when he would hear anything against Khadijah رضي الله عنها.
And this shows us an aspect of the personality of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
his loyalty to the people who were close to him.
This is years after Khadijah(خديجه) passed away.
I mean, opportunist people, they take advantage of a person
and whenever that person is gone, that's the end of the relationship.
Rasool Allah ﷺ would always remember his old friends, old relatives
Hamza Bin Abdul Muttalib(حمزه بن عبدالمطلب), Khadijah رضي الله عنها, Mus'ab Bin Umair(مصعب بن عمير),
these Sahabah(صحابه), in fact, Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), one amazing thing that brings the person to tears.
Before Rasool Allah ﷺ passed away, one of the last things he did.
Was go and visit the cemetery of his friends, who died in the Battle of Uhud(احد).
The 70 companions, who died in the Battle of Uhud(احد),
when Rasool Allah ﷺ felt that he will be leaving Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) soon,
he went to the cemetery and made Dua(دُعَا) for them
and he was saying in that Dua(دُعَا) that soon we will meet.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was missing them so much.
And was asking Allah سبحانه وتعالى to bring him with them and to join them together in Jannah(جنة).
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ have this strong relationship with his Sahabah(صحابه) and loyalty,
and he never forgot his wife Khadijah(خديجه), who stood with him in moments of difficulty,
he never forgot that and he would continuously make Dua(دُعَا) for her and mention her name.
And Khadijah(خديجه) was a special person, Khadijah رضي الله عنها,
when she was living Jibril(جبريل) descended on Muhammadﷺ and said:
Khadijah(خديجه) is going to approach you now and she's carrying for you some food
When she arrives, tell her that Allah is giving her Salam(سلام)
and tell her that I am giving her Salam(سلام).
That is how special Khadijah(خديجه) was.
Allahسبحانه وتعالى sends down Jibreel عليه السّلام, to tell Khadijah(خديجه) that I'm giving Salam(سلام) to you.
And Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل) is then adding his own Salam(سلام) to the statement
and telling Muhammadﷺ and tell her that Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل) is giving her, his Salam(سلام).
And then Jibreel عليه السّلام said:
And give her the glad tidings of a palace in paradise.
So, she was granted a place in Jannah(جنة).
Khadijah(خديجه) is one of the four Greatest Women that ever lived.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says that the greatest women that ever set foot on the face of the earth are four,
Maryam Bint Imran(مريم بنت عمران),
Khadijah Bint Khuwailid(خديجه بنت خويلد),
Fatimah Bint Muhammad(فاطمه بنت محمد)
and Aasiya Bint Muzahim(آسيه بنت مزاحم).
These are the greatest women.
The greatest among them is Maryam عليها السّلام by the verse in Qur'an.
وَإِذْ قَالَتِ الْمَلَائِكَةُ يَا مَرْيَمُ إِنَّ اللَّهَ اصْطَفَاكِ وَطَهَّرَكِ وَاصْطَفَاكِ عَلَىٰ نِسَاءِ الْعَالَمِينَ۝
O Maryam(مريم) Allah has chosen you, above all of the women of the world
by the statement of Qur'an.
Second, is Khadijah(خديجه), she's number two, the second greatest women,
number three, Fatima Bint Muhammad(فاطمه بنت محمد), and number four, Aasiya Bint Muzahim(آسيه بنت مزاحم)
and all of these four women had something to do with a Nabi(نبي).
Two of them were Mothers of Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء), or actually ones, who brought up Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء),
Maryam عليها السّلام brought up Eesa(عيسى),
she was his mother and Aasiya(آسيه) she brought up Musa(موسى).
And then Khadijah(خديجه) was a wife of a Nabi(نبي) and Fatimah(فاطمه) was the daughter of a Nabi(نبي).
Rasool Allah ﷺ, number one reached the age of 25.
And he was, Yaani(يعني) in his seerah(سيرة), Rasool Allah ﷺ was known as being chaste
in an environment that is corrupt.
And the reason why I'm bringing this up, is because, the some of the orientalist,
the ones, who are professional enemies of Islam,
they use that as their animosity towards Islam.
It is their role in life, they try to attack the person, of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
In one of the areas that they attack is his marriage life.
They talk a lot about his marriage to Ayesha(عائشه).
They talk about the fact that he married 12 women
and they try to accuse Muhammadﷺ of being a womanizer.
So, let's look at the marriage life of Rasool Allah ﷺ, let's study it.
Number one, Rasool Allah ﷺ reaches to the age of 25.
In an environment where Zina(زنا), adultery and fornication was widespread.
And you might have read the Hadith(حديث) of Ayesha(عائشه), which was in Bukhari(بخاريْ),
where she talks about the four different relationships that existed between men and women.
One of them was a traditional marriage.
The other one was brothels that were legal in Makkah, and they would have flags on top of them,
as signs for anybody who was interested in this corrupt behavior.
And then they had this other type of relationship,
where a woman would sleep with a group of men, that could go up to 10.
And then if she becomes pregnant, and she delivers, then she can call these men in
and say that she could just pick anyone out of them and say that you are the father of the child.
They had this strange relationship where a man would allow his wife to sleep with a noble man,
in order to have some noble lineage.
So, it was quite a corrupt environment.
A young man would party and sleep with a woman that they have no legal relationship with.
Rasool Allah ﷺ lives up until the age of 25,
and he was able to fight the tide, and stay away from all of this corruption,
all the way until he reached the age of 25,
so, that's number one.
Number two, at the age of 25, he chooses to marry a woman who was 15 years older than himself,
and she is a widow, or divorced.
Now, Rasool Allah ﷺ being from the noble family of Bannu Haashim(بنو هاشم),
he could have chosen for himself any woman he wanted in Makkah.
And if he was interested in these desires,
he would have chosen for himself a young woman to marry.
Rather than marrying a lady, who is 15 years older than him.
She was 40 years old, when Rasool Allah ﷺ married her.
Number three, Rasool Allah ﷺ remains with Khadijah(خديجه), until he reaches the age of 50.
And we know that the age in which men would have strong desires towards women,
would be from young age to around the age of 50.
I mean, that's the young age of a man when the desires would be the strongest.
So, for Rasool Allah ﷺ to remain married to Khadijah(خديجه) in a very happy marriage.
And it is not reported at all, that Rasool Allah ﷺ had any intentions
of marrying anybody else, he didn't even contemplate the idea,
there are no reports of that.
So, for Rasool Allah ﷺ to continue with Khadijah رضي الله عنها from the age of 25 to the age of 50,
is a clear indication that Rasool Allah ﷺ had none of those thoughts in his mind,
and I think this completely destroys that argument.
Khadijah رضي الله عنها passes away, Rasool Allah ﷺ remains as a bachelor for about two to three years.
Later on, he marries another widow Syeda Saoda رضي الله عنها
the reasons for him marrying Saoda(سوده), are because Saoda رضي الله عنها was in Abyssinia,
she came back to Makkah and her husband passed away.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ out of his care for his companions, he married her,
her husband died she doesn't have anyone to provide for her
Rasool Allah ﷺ marries her and she was quite old in age.
Because later on, in Madina, we know that Saoda(سوده) ended up giving up her night to Ayesha رضي الله عنها,
because she was very old at age.
Suddenly, within the last 10 years of Rasool Allah ﷺ, Rasool Allah ﷺ married many women,
to the extent that when he died, he left behind nine widows.
So, how come this change, from the age of 25 to 50 he only married Khadijah رضي الله عنها.
But then, within the last 10 years of his life, it's 10 years
because for two or three years, he was unmarried for the last 10 years of his life.
He marries and he leaves behind nine widows.
What is the reason?
Number one, forging alliances with different tribes.
When we study the marriage life of Rasool Allah ﷺ ,
we need to look at the life of Rasool Allah ﷺ, comprehensively.
The Messenger of Allah, Muhammadﷺ devoted all of his efforts,
underline all, all of his efforts for the promotion of Islam,
everything that he would do, even his decision in marriage, would be based on the benefit of Islam.
Whatever Rasool Allah ﷺ did in his life, the intention of it, was to promote the religion of Allah.
He wouldn't do anything purely to satisfy his human desires, he would do it to please Allahعَزّ وجَلّ.
Therefore, we need to look at his marriage life in this light.
He married a few of his wives to forge alliances with different tribes to bring them closer to Islam,
like his marriage of Juwairiyyah(جويريه),
which ended up making the whole tribe of Bannu Mustalaq(بنو مصطلق) become Muslim.
Number two, caring for his companions,
his followers like the example we gave of Saoda رضي الله عنها.
Number three, Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted to strengthen his ties with his closest companions.
Rasool Allah ﷺ had a strong brotherly feeling towards his companions.
And there was a special group among them whom Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted to have a stronger relationship.
And that is not only an Islamic brotherhood, but to add to it, family ties.
And for someone who did not experience Islamic brotherhood,
it's difficult for them to appreciate this. What if you have lived like,
Rasool Allah ﷺ with his companions for 23 years, what bond would develop between them?
They were Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) together in moments of ease and moments of difficulty,
on the battlefield and in times of peace, they would eat together, they would travel together,
the relationship that Rasool Allah ﷺ had with the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم was so strong.
When we get into the Madina era, and we talk about the time, when Rasool Allah ﷺ passed away
and the feelings that were in Madina, the feelings of loss, that the people of Madina had,
it is something that we cannot even describe.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted to strengthen the relationship between him and his close companions.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ married the daughter of Abu Bakr(ابو بكر),
and he married the daughter of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب),
And he married his daughter to Uthman Bin Affan(عثمان ابن عفان).
And when this daughter of Rasool Allah ﷺ passed away,
he married Uthman(عثمان), another of his daughters.
And then she passed away, Rasool Allah ﷺ said: If I had 99 daughters,
I would marry them to Uthman Bin Affan(عثمان ابن عفان) one after another.
Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted to have this relationship between him and Uthman Bin Affan(عثمان ابن عفان)
and he married his most beloved daughter, Fatimah رضي الله عنها to Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب).
So, now he has a family relationship between him and the four Khulafaa(خلفاء)
Abu Bakr(ابو بكر), Umar(عمر), Uthman(عثمان) and Ali(علي).
Number four, and this is very important.
Conveying the religion,
we are to follow the Sunnah(سنة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ, he has a Sunnah(سنة) as a statesman,
a Sunnah(سنة) as a teacher, a Sunnah(سنة) as an Imam(امام), a Sunnah(سنة) as a military leader,
and he has a Sunnah(سنة), as a family man.
Now, we have hundreds of companions to convey to us, his Sunnah(سنة) as a statesmen.
We have hundreds of companions to tell us, how he acted as a military leader.
We have hundreds of companions to tell us, how he was as a teacher and as an Imam(اِمَام),
how many do we have to tell us about his family life?
How many.?
Rasool Allah ﷺ did not have a lot of children that survived him, only Fatimah رضي الله عنها.
So, who would convey to us his family life, it is his wives.
Now if Rasool Allah ﷺ only had one wife.
First of all, it will be difficult on this one wife to recall every aspect of the family life of Rasool ﷺ.
Number two, she could easily be discredited because you only have one source.
And we know that Abu Hurairah(أبو هريره),
we know the vicious attack that is being directed at Abu Hurairah رضي الله عنه.
Because the enemies of Islam know that if they can discredit Abu Hurairah رضي الله عنه.
They can completely destroy over 5000 of the sayings of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
By discrediting one man, they could undermine 5000s of the Ahadith(احاديث) of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And you already know that that has happened for a fact
there is an attack on Abu Hurairah رضي الله عنه.
And the family life of Rasool Allah ﷺ is one of the most important aspects of his Sunnah(سنة)
because it relates to every one of us.
Not every one of us will be an Imam(اِمَام) not everyone will be a military leader, not everyone will be a statesman,
not everyone will be a teacher.
But almost everyone in the Ummah(امة) will be a member of a family.
So, how will they learn on how to conduct their lives as members of a family
without receiving information about how Rasool Allah ﷺ was a family man.
Therefore, Rasool Allah ﷺ had multiple wives,
so that they would convey to us this body of knowledge of how Rasool Allah ﷺ acted in his private life.?
Many of the Sunnan(سُنَنْ), relating to, how Rasool Allah ﷺ treated his wives?
How he treated his servants, how he ate, how he dressed, how he would spend his time at home,
his Ibadah(عبادة) at night.
That was all conveyed to us by the wives of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, it's not only limited to the section of family Sunnah(سنة),
but it also relates to the Ibadah(عبادة) how Rasool Allah ﷺ would spend his night?
How do we know that.?
It was through the wives of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, having multiple wives, first of all, they compensate each other.
So, if one of them forgets the other would remember.
Number two,
you have more than one chain of narration, it's coming through multiple sources, rather than one.
And Number three, it becomes impossible to discredit because now we have more than one person involved.
And that is an extremely important thing for us.
And remember, Allah سبحانه وتعالى has sent Muhammadﷺ as a living embodiment of Qur'an,
and therefore Allah granted that His Sunnah(سنة) will reached to us
because it's part of the promise of Allah to protect Qur'an.
The protection of Qur'an is not only that the words of Qur'an will be protected,
but also part of its interpretation, by Rasool Allah ﷺ would survive.
And that was done through the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم
and most importantly through the wives of Rasool Ullah صلوات الله وسلام عليه.
So, for us, it was very critical for the Ummah(امة) that Rasool Allah ﷺ has multiple wives,
and that's why he was excluded from the ruling of having four or less.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى has allowed him to have more,
because of the special circumstances of Muhammadﷺ.
This was done and destined by Allah سبحانه وتعالى as a protection of His religion.
Now, the two most controversial marriages of Rasool Allah ﷺ are, his marriage to Ayesha(عائشه)
and his marriage to Zainab Bint Jahash(زينب بنت جحش).
These are the most targeted marriages of Rasool Allah ﷺ, you don't have a lot of complain
about his marriage to Umm Salamah(ام سلمه) or Umm Habibah(ام حبيبه) or Saodah(سوده).
But there's a lot of attack directed at his marriage to Ayesha رضي الله عنها
and Zainab Bint Jahash(زينب بنت جحش).
Ayesha رضي الله عنها because Rasool Allah ﷺ married her at the age of six,
and the marriage was consummated at the age of nine.
And the attack against Zainab Bint Jahash(زينب بنت جحش) is because, she was married to his adopted son.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ married her later on.
So, these are the two marriages where you have a lot of controversy.
So, let's look at these two particular cases.
Subhaan Allah(سبحان الله), it so happens that the two particular marriages that are targeted,
are the only two marriages of Rasool Allah ﷺ that were divinely instructed,
none of the other marriages of Rasool Allah ﷺ, were instructed by Allah, except these two.
His marriage to Zainab(زينب) was instructed in Qur'an in Surah Al-Ahzaab(سورة الاحزاب).
وَإِذْ تَقُولُ لِلَّذِي أَنْعَمَ اللَّهُ عَلَيْهِ وَأَنْعَمْتَ عَلَيْهِ أَمْسِكْ عَلَيْكَ زَوْجَكَ وَاتَّقِ اللَّهَ
وَاتَّقِ اللَّهَ وَتُخْفِي فِي نَفْسِكَ مَا اللَّهُ مُبْدِيهِ وَتَخْشَى النَّاسَ
وَتَخْشَى النَّاسَ وَاللَّهُ أَحَقُّ أَنْ تَخْشَاهُ ۖ
فَلَمَّا قَضَىٰ زَيْدٌ مِنْهَا وَطَرًا زَوَّجْنَاكَهَا لِكَيْ لَا يَكُونَ عَلَى الْمُؤْمِنِينَ حَرَجٌ
لِكَيْ لَا يَكُونَ عَلَى الْمُؤْمِنِينَ حَرَجٌ فِي أَزْوَاجِ أَدْعِيَائِهِمْ إِذَا قَضَوْا مِنْهُنَّ وَطَرًا ۚ
وَكَانَ أَمْرُ اللَّهِ مَفْعُولًاَ۝
When Zaid(زيد) left her, we commanded you to marry her, so it's in Qur'an.
And the marriage of Rasool Allah ﷺ to Ayesha(عائشه) was divinely inspired
through the dream which Rasool Allah ﷺ saw, and this dream is mentioned in Bukhari(بخاريْ).
Rasool Allah ﷺ says: Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل) came to me, and I saw you, Ayesha(عائشه)
covered behind a silk curtain, or you were wearing a silk dress.
And when I would uncover you, this is in the dream before Rasool Allah ﷺ marries her.
When I uncovered you, I saw you, and Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل) told me, this is your wife.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ saw a woman and when he took a look at her, it was Ayesha(عائشه).
And then Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل) told him, this is your wife, in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) and in Akhirah(آخرة)
and Rasool Allah ﷺ saw this dream twice.
And we know that the dreams of the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) are Revelation.
رُعْيَ الْاَنْبِيَاءَ وَحِيْ
Rasool Allah ﷺ says that the dreams of Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) are revelation.
So, the marriage of Rasool Ullah to Ayesha(عائشه), is instructed by Allah,
and the marriage of Rasool Allah ﷺ to Zainab(زينب) was instructed by Allah.
So, we have two types of people, who would attack this.
One type would be Muslims, who have weak faith
and they wonder how Rasool Allah ﷺ would do something like this.
The respond to them would be it wasn't Rasool Allah ﷺ who did it.
He was commanded by Allah to do it.
So, as a Muslim, do you believe in the commands of Allah or not?
It was an exceptional situation that is not allowed for you.
That's why it's not part of the Sunnah(سنة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ, we cannot marry more than four.
That's not part of the Sunnah(سنة) that we follow.
And also, his situation with Ayesha رضي الله عنها is also not something that is allowed for us.
It was an exception that was allowed for Rasool Allah ﷺ, for particular reasons, which I will talk about.
But for a Muslim this would be the response,
that these were divinely commanded by Allahعَزّوجَلّ therefore we have no right to question them.
It wasn't something that was initiated by Muhammadﷺ, it was done by Allah.
Now, for the ones, who are not Muslim and are attacking Rasool Allah ﷺ and saying that
this is an act of you know, all of the horrible accusations that are directed at Rasool Allah ﷺ.
The response will be that your problem is not really Rasool Allah ﷺ marrying to Ayesha(عائشه),
your problem is that you don't believe he's the Messenger of Allah.
You don't believe that he's receiving revelation.
So, your problem runs deeper.
The issue of bringing up Ayesha(عائشه) is just a front, in order to attack Islam,
even if I Rasool Allah ﷺ didn't do it, you would still be attacking.
You can still say that this was divinely instructed, the response will be well, how convenient it is,
whenever there is something that seems strange, you say that God commanded it.
That could be a response.
I mean, they would say, well, these particular two marriages that we are attacking, you say that
God is one, Who instructed them,
the response will be that we need to then discuss the issue of whether Rasool Allah ﷺ was a prophet of Allah or not.?
And that would settle the argument.
If he is the Prophet of Allah, then we have no right to question what Allah سبحانه وتعالى told him to do.
I mean, if we establish that he was a Messenger of Allah receiving revelation from Allah,
then whatever Allah tells him to do, we should accept it.
I mean, if Allah tells one of us to stand against the wall with one feet up in the air, until we die,
we have no right to question that.
I mean, it's God, who's instructing us to do it.
Who am I, to go against what my Creator wants me to do?
Allah owes nothing to us, and we owe everything to Him.
Therefore, if something is instructed by Allah, I don't have to understand, why it is
that I'm instructed to do this, I just have to do it.
So, I hope that we get the point here that
the enemies of Islam are attacking the marriage of Rasool Allah ﷺ to Ayesha(عائشه),
even if that didn't happen, the attack would still continue.
Because their problem is that they don't believe in Islam.
They don't believe that Muhammad Rasool Allah ﷺ is the Messenger of Allah.
They don't believe that he was receiving revelations from Allah.
So, it's pointless to argue on the point of Ayesha رضي الله عنها, because there's a major problem,
and that's they don't accept him altogether.
And that would take us back to the accusations of the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)
that were thrown at Muhammadﷺ, Allahعَزّ وجَلّ revealed:
قَدْ نَعْلَمُ إِنَّهُ لَيَحْزُنُكَ الَّذِي يَقُولُونَ ۖ
فَإِنَّهُمْ لَا يُكَذِّبُونَكَ وَلَٰكِنَّ الظَّالِمِينَ بِآيَاتِ اللَّهِ يَجْحَدُونَ۝
They are not disbelieving you, they are believing in the Message of Allah.
They are attacking you because you are the Messenger.
They're not attacking your personality, just because of your personality.
They're attacking you because you're conveying the message of Allah to them.
So, these attacks that are hurdled at Muhammadﷺ are because,
he is the Messenger of Allah.
Now, the marriage of Rasool Allah ﷺ to Ayesha(عائشه) how come, it was so important.
Let me make this statement first.
One of the greatest blessings of Allah on us as Muslims.
Again, one of the greatest blessings of Allah on us
as Muslims is that Rasool Allah ﷺ married Ayesha(عائشه).
This particular marriage that some people have doubts in their heart.
Due to the fact that Rasool Allah ﷺ marries a girl who's six years old,
they do not realize that it would have been a disaster on the Ummah(امة) if Rasool Allah ﷺ did not marry Ayesha(عائشه).
It is one of the best things that happened to us.
Ayesha رضي الله عنها had a mind of a scholar.
She had very bright mind, very intelligent, and she had an inquisitive nature,
Ayesha رضي الله عنها describes herself and says;
The companions of Rasool Allah ﷺ used to hear the Hadith(حديث) of Rasool Ullah and they would immediately follow it.
While I would ask Rasool Allah ﷺ questions about it.
Ayesha رضي الله عنها being the wife of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and being the most beloved of his wives had this informal relationship with Rasool Allah ﷺ,
so she could afford to question him and ask him,
while the others were very respectful of Rasool Allah ﷺ, and they wouldn't dare do that.
So, it needed somebody who had this intimate relationship with Rasool Allah ﷺ to be able to ask questions.
And to inquire about the certain statements of Rasool Allah ﷺ and remember, we talked about Amr Bil Aas(عمرو بن عاص),
and we said how much he loved Rasool Allah ﷺ and when he was dying, he said:
If you would ask me to describe to you, Rasool Allah ﷺ I wouldn't be able to do so.
Because I had so much love and admiration and respect for him, I lived with him for years,
and I couldn't even look him straight in the eye,
because of the deep respect that I had for Rasool Allah ﷺ.
But Ayesha رضي الله عنها, being very young, and playful at that age,
and having a very close relationship with Rasool Allah ﷺ,
Rasool Allah could say something, and she would ask
and she would argue with Rasool Allah ﷺ, no one else could afford to do that.
So, we learned so much because of that.
Plus, Ayesha رضي الله عنها had a mind of a scholar, and she became one of the greatest scholars of Islam.
Among the top seven narrators of Hadith(حديث), Ayesha(عائشه) comes number four.
Ayesha(عائشه) is one of the top seven narrators of the Hadith(حديث) of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Number one is Abu Hurairah(إبو هريره), five thousand plus,
Number two, Abdullah Bin Umar (عبد الله بن عمر) Two Thousand Six Hundred(2600),
Number three Anas Ibn Malik(انس ابن مالك),
Number four Ayesha رضي الله عنها, Two Thousand Two Hundred(2200).
So, really the differences between rank four, three and two is not much.
Abu Huraira(ابو هريره) is the one, who is outstanding, he is almost double the second place.
Open on a book of fiqh(فقه),
it's impossible to study a book of Fiqh(فقه) without going through the name of Ayesha(عائشه),
her narrations and her opinions, in Fiqh(فقه),
in every Fiqh(فقه), Hanafi(حنفي), Shafie(شافعي), Hanbali(حنبلي), Maliki(مالكي),
Ayesha رضي الله عنها her knowledge is there.
So, we have learned so much from Ayesha رضي الله عنها, it was the destiny of Allah
that Rasool Allah ﷺ would marry Ayesha رضي الله عنها.
And it was just as it was a divine inspiration to Rasool Allah ﷺ, maybe he didn't think about it.
Before it was a surprise to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
When Rasool Allah ﷺ went and proposed to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) that he wants to marry his daughter,
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(ابوبكرالصديق)  was surprised.
He said: I am your brother.
Meaning, we're very close in age, I am your brother.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: You are my brother,
وَبْنَتُكَ تَصْلُحُلِيْ
And your daughter is appropriate for me.
This was a command from Allahعَزّ وجَلّ.
And Subhaan Allah(سبحان الله), it was a blessing from Allahعَزّ وجَلّ on this Ummah(امة).
Sometimes, something would appear to be in a certain way.
However, if we just dig a little bit deeper, we would see something completely different.
وَعَسَىٰ أَنْ تَكْرَهُوا شَيْئًا وَهُوَ خَيْرٌ لَكُمْ ۖ
You might dislike something but there's a lot of good for you in it.
So, we should be very proud and happy
that Rasool Allah ﷺ married Ayesha رضي الله عنها and we should be thankful to Allah that, that happened.
Rather than having these doubts in our hearts and having this fear and inhibition.
It is a blessing of Allahعَزّ وجَلّ on us.
Just a final comment Rasool Allah ﷺ did not marry any virgin woman except Ayesha رضي الله عنها.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ never married any woman who was young except Ayesha رضي الله عنها.
It was an exceptional case.
If we want to study the marriage life of Rasool Allah ﷺ that was initiated by him.
We need to look at every wife except Ayesha(عائشه) and Zainab(زينب).
And you'll know, who are the women Rasool Allahﷺ was married, Saoda(سودة).
Forgot to mention, Umm Habiba(ام حبيبه),
Umm Habiba رضي الله عنها, she's the one, who migrated to Abyssinia
and her husband Obaid Ellah Bin Jahash(عبيدالله بن جحش) converted to Christianity.
And she went through a miserable time, very difficult moments on Umm Habiba(ام حبيبه),
being the daughter of Abu Sufiyan(ابو سفيان), the head of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
So, later on her husband passed away.
Rasool Allah ﷺ sent a message, letter with Amr Bin Ummayya Ad-Dhamri(عمرو بن اميه أضمري), to An-Najashi(النجاشي)
asking An-Najashi(النجاشي) to marry him to Umm Habiba رضي الله عنها
because Rasool Allah ﷺ had sympathy for what Umm Habiba(ام حبيبه) went through.
Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted to marry her even though she was hundreds of miles away.
The scholars say that was the furthest marriage of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
She was in Abyssinia and he was in Madina.
So, it was symbolic to first of all take care of Umm Habiba(ام حبيبه).
Also, Umm Habiba(ام حبيبه) was the daughter of Abu Sufiyan(ابو سفيان).
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted to bring the staunchest enemies of Islam closer,
he wants to soften their stance.
And when Abu Sufiyan(ابو سفيان) heard of the news that Rasool Allah ﷺ married his daughter,
even though Abu Sufiyan(ابو سفيان) was now the leader of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
He was their leader in fighting Islam.
Abu Sufiyan(ابو سفيان) was happy that this marriage took place.
He said and who is better to marry than Muhammadﷺ.
I mean, Abu Sufiyan(ابو سفيان) knows the lineage of Muhammadﷺ.
So, that's how he looks at it.
This is the from Bannu Hashim(بنو هاشم), it's an honor for us to marry our daughter to somebody from Bannu Hashim(بنو هاشم).
Our issue with him is because of religion.
So, he was proud and happy that his daughter got married to Muhammadﷺ.
So, that's softened Abu Sufiyan(ابو سفيان) a little bit, it brought him closer to Islam.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ also intended in taking care of Umm Habiba رضي الله عنها,
in that difficult moments that she was going through.
Another marriage would be Umm Salamah(ام سلمه),
Umm Salamah رضي الله عنها also was one of the ones, who made Hijrah(هجرة) to Abyssinia,
then they came back and they went to Madina.
Later on, Abu Salamah(ابو سلمه), passed away Rasool Allah ﷺ married Umm Salamah(ام سلمه).
So, he would take care of the wives of his companions, who died and these are older women,
but Rasool Allah ﷺ is the father of this Ummah(امة).
Just like his wives are called mothers of the Ummah(امة).
What's the name given to the wives of Rasool Allah ﷺ, Ummahaat Ul Mo'mineen(أمهات المؤمنين),
the mothers of the believers.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ viewed himself as a caretaker of this Ummah(امة).
Even if he doesn't have a direct blood relationship with the members of this Ummah(امة),
he still felt that he is their father, so he would take care of their needy,
he would take care of the hungry,
and that's conversation that happened between Asma Bint Umais(اسماء بنت عميس) and Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب)
when Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said: We have more rights to Rasool Allah ﷺ then you.
Because we made Hijrah(هجرة) before you.
Asma Bint Umais(اسماء بنت عميس), she just arrived from Abyssinia.
Asma Bint Umais(اسماء بنت عميس) responded by saying; No, that's not true.
You were with Rasool Allah ﷺ,
يُطْعِمُ جَآئِعَكُمْ
He was feeding the hungry among you,
وَيُعَلِّمْ جَاهِلَكُمْ
And was teaching the ignorant among you.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ was the father of this Ummah(امة),
and that is how, his marriage life, even is a reflection of that.
An important event occurred during the Prophet Hood of Muhammadﷺ.
A flood has affected the structure of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه),
Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) is located in a low valley between mountains.
And Makkah was once flooded.
And the flood has caused cracks in the walls of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
So, the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) felt the need to rebuild Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) again.
Now Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) in total has been built and rebuilt five or four times,
depending on, who was the first to build it.
There's a difference of opinion on whether Ibrahim عليه السّلام was the first to build Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
Some scholars refer to our father Adam عليه السّلام as the first one to build Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
However, the majority opinion is that it was Ibrahim عليه السّلام, who first built it.
Now, the ones who say that Adam عليه السّلام is the one, who built it,
they say will not contradicting Qur'an, because Qur'an says;
وَإِذْ يَرْفَعُ إِبْرَاهِيمُ الْقَوَاعِدَ مِنَ الْبَيْتِ وَإِسْمَاعِيلُ رَبَّنَا تَقَبَّلْ مِنَّا ۖ
إِنَّكَ أَنْتَ السَّمِيعُ الْعَلِيمُ۝
They say that Qur'an states that Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) was raising the foundations of the house.
Meaning there was already something there for him to raise above it.
So, they say that the house, the foundations of it, were established in the time of Adam عليه السّلام.
But the common belief among our scholars is that
it was Ibrahim عليه السّلام, who first built it.
However, there is no dispute in the holiness of the place, since the earth was created.
I mean, all of our scholars say even if it wasn't Adam(آدم), who first built it,
the place was sacred, was holy, and was visited by the Prophets of Allah.
So, they say it used to be like a small hill, which was destined as a sacred and holy place.
And the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) of Allah would visit it.
And we have references of quite a few Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء), visiting the house of Allah.
There's a Hadith(حديث) that states that Hood(هود) visited Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه),
there's a Hadith(حديث) that says that Salih(صالح) visited, Noah(نوح)
and there's a saying attributed to Rasool Allah ﷺ that Eesa عليه السّلام when he comes down again,
when he descends to earth in a second coming, he will make Hajj(حج).
So, it's either Adam(آدم) or Ibrahim عليه السّلام who first built Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه),
but we all know that, it was the first house built for the remembrance of Allah.
إِنَّ أَوَّلَ بَيْتٍ وُضِعَ لِلنَّاسِ لَلَّذِي بِبَكَّةَ مُبَارَكًا وَهُدًى لِلْعَالَمِينَ۝
First house established for My worship was the one in Bakkah(بكة),
Bakkah(بكة) is also another name for Makkah.
So, you have Adam(آدم) and Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم).
Let's start counting from Ibrahim عليه السّلام, so Ibrahim عليه السّلام is the first.
Second time was this time we're talking about now, when Makkah was flooded.
The people Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) wanted to rebuild it.
They gathered together and they had to tear it down.
But none of them agreed to make that move.
So, they're all waiting ready with their equipment around Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
But no one wants to go ahead and start bringing down
that is how much honor and respect they had for Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) in their hearts,
even though at the time they were Mushrikeen(مشركين).
But they feared Allah سبحانه وتعالى and they thought that it's a dangerous thing to tear down the walls of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
And then one of them said:
I will be the first to do it, and he gathered all of his sons and
they came early in the morning, and they started bringing the rocks of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) down and they were saying;
O Allah, Don't be afraid, all what we want is good.
So, you can see, their also, their false understanding of the divinity of Allah سبحانه وتعالى.
They were trying to calm God, by telling don't be afraid all what we want is good,
Allah سبحانه وتعالى knows what's in your hearts, you don't have to tell him that.
So, even though they believed in Allah, but the in terms of the attributes of Allah.
اَلْاَسْمَاءُ الصِّفَاتْ
They had some problems with that.
So, they brought down the walls of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
Now it happened that there was a Roman ship that crashed on a port on the Red Sea close to Makkah.
So, they brought some of the wood on that ship.
And there was a Roman builder who was on that ship.
So, they also had him help with the wood.
So, this was the first time they made the roof of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه), the ceiling of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) from wood.
They use some of the wood from this ship.
Now the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), they knew that money from interest was no good.
And they made a decision that they're only going to use Halal(حلال) money, in the rebuilding of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
They're not going to use money from interest or money from prostitution,
because at that time to show their corruptness.
And by the way, there's a Hadith(حديث) that is narrated by Al-Bukhari(بخاريْ).
Ayesha رضي الله عنها talks about the types of marriages that existed in Arabia.
It's on page 11, you can refer to it later on.
But the prostitution was something that existed, and you would have men hiring their slave girls,
as an income generating source for them.
But they knew that this was not good.
They would do it, they would deal with interest.
So, they decided that they're not going to use this money in the rebuilding of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
Since they ran short of funds.
They ended up shortening Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه),
You know Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) originally was a bit of a rectangle rather than a square.
It was rectangular in shape.
Because the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) ran short of funds.
They ended up shortening Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) from one side.
So, they made it a square rather than a rectangle to save money.
The area of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه), which they left out was, what we refer today as Al-Hijr(ألحجر),
the enclosed area in that semi circle, if you ever visited Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه),
you would see that on one side of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه), there's a semi circle
that used to be part of the original building of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
And Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) also had two gates, they made it one and they raised the doorstep.
So, now in order to get access to the door, you have to climb, the gate was made very high.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says in this Hadith(حديث),
don't, you know
Rasool Ullah is talking to Ayesha(عائشه),
don't you know that your people had insufficient funds for the expenses.
If it were not, for the fact that your people were only recently unbelievers,
I would have torn down the Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) and made for it one door on the east and another on the west,
and I would have included the Al-Hijr(الحجر) area within it.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ opened Makkah, he was thinking about reconstructing Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) on the original foundations.
But then he told Ayesha(عائشه), the reason I'm not going to do this.?
Is because your people just became Muslim, their Islam is soft, their Eeman(إيمان) is weak.
And it might be a Fitnah(فِتْنَه) for them, it might cause them a problem, if I reconstruct Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
So he didn't do it.
There's an important lesson to learn from this Hadith(حديث), and that is that
the Daiyah(داعيه) needs to take the condition of the people into consideration.
Even though Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted to do this, but he didn't,
because he was worried that it might affect the Eeman(إيمان) of the people.
So, as a person who's calling to Islam, you need to take into consideration,
the condition of the people that you're directing the message to.
Abdullah Bin Masood(عبد الله بن مسعود) says that if you tell the people something that is beyond
their comprehension, or understanding or Eeman(إيمان), it might be a trial for some of them.
It might cause the backlash with some people.
Sometimes we throw out information on a particular subject, which is absolutely true and valid.
But because the people are not ready for it yet, because their Eeman(إيمان) is weak,
it causes a backlash with them.
Some things people just are unable to grasp.
Now, Rasool Allah ﷺ said that your people, Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
the reason why they made the door of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) high
is because they wanted to have control on who, would go in and out.
It was an issue of power.
They didn't want to make the door low, so that it would be accessible to anyone.
They made it high so that they could control who would go in and out it's a matter of influence, having authority.
So, the door of the Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) was raised.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: If I would rebuild it, I would lower the gate.
And I would make for it two gates,
so that people could come from one side and leave from the other.
Rather than having to come in and out from the same door.
Rasool Allah ﷺ participated in the rebuilding of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
And at the time, he was maybe around 35 years old.
That's a rough estimate.
So, now the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) are building Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه),
they reached to the holiest part of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه), which is the Blackstone.
And now disputes erupts among them, who will have the honor to place the Blackstone in its spot.
Because when they were rebuilding Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه),
every tribe took responsibility of building one side of it,
they all want to participate in this honor.
But with the black stone they disputed,
every tribe wanted to have the honor of putting it in its place.
Bannu Abdd-ud-Da'ar(بنو عبدالدار) they gathered all of their men,
and they came in front of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) with a pot of blood.
And they placed it in front of everyone.
And they all stuck their hands in the blood and pulled it out.
In other words, they're telling everyone
that this is what will happen if we don't place the Blackstone in its place.
So, it's like pledging to die and to fight.
We will do it otherwise, this is what will happen, blood will flow.
Even though that was a drastic measure, and quite a threat.
But that wasn't enough to deter others,
another tribe they went and bought in their own pot of blood.
And they started sticking their hands in and pulling them out.
And then everybody was bringing their own pots of blood and
it was four or five days they couldn't solve the problem and war was about to erupt between them.
And then the eldest man among them, Umayyah(أميه), he had a suggestion.
He came and said: Let's agree that the first man to walk in, towards Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه),
will be given complete authority in judging between us.
So, they all gather next to Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) and, they were waiting for the first person to come.
And the first person to walk in was Muhammadﷺ
they all stood up and said:
اَلْصَادِقُ الْاَمِيْن رَضِيْنَه رَضِيْنَهْ
The truthful and the trustworthy, we all agree.
Now they have already agreed that they will give complete authority to the person who would come in,
but they were so happy
that, this person was Muhammadﷺ because they knew that he will not be biased in his ruling.
You know, it would be expected that if someone came from a particular family,
he would give authority to his family to place it in it's place.
I mean, and that was the expected thing that we're going to leave it randomly
for the first one to come in, and his family would take it,
but when they saw that it was Muhammadﷺ, they were so happy because they know his fairness.
So, they told him, we give you complete authority in solving this dispute.
Rasool Allah ﷺ asked them to bring a robe, a piece of cloth.
He picked up the black stone and placed it, on this cloth.
And then he asked a representative from each clan to hold the cloth from one side.
And then they all raised it up together, in the same time.
Therefore every one of them will participate in lifting the black stone.
And when they all lifted it up,
then heﷺ, with his blessed hands picked up the black stone and placed it in, its place.
So, it was Rasool Allah ﷺ who put the Blackstone in its spot.
So that's the second time Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) was rebuilt.
Rasool Allah ﷺ opened Makkah and then he said that if it wasn't for the fact that the people are new Muslims,
I would have rebuilt it on the foundations of Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم).
Years later, Abdullah Bin Zubair(عبدالله بن زبير) became the Ameer(امير) of Makkah.
He knew of this Hadith(حديث), because Ayesha(عائشه) was his aunt.
Abdullah Bin Zubair(عبدالله بن زبير), his mother is Asma Bint Abi Bakr(أسماء بنت ابي بكر) the sister of Ayesha(عائشه),
so Ayesha(عائشه) was his aunt and he was familiar with this Hadith(حديث).
So, he decided to rebuild Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) on the original foundations
because now the people have been Muslim for a long time.
They are not new Muslims anymore, they will be able to handle the situation.
He decided that he's gonna rebuild Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) especially that Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) was burnt
because Al-Hajjaj Bin Yousaf Al-Thaqafi(ألحجاج بن يوسف أثقفي), he has laid siege on Makkah.
At that time, there was a war between Abdullah Bin Zubair(عبدالله بن زبير),
and Banni Ummayayah(بني أمية) in Syria.
And the Army General of Bannu Umayyah(بنو امية) has laid siege to Makkah.
And one of the catapults has hit Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) and it caused some damage and it burned.
Now that damage could have been fixed without tearing down Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه),
but Abdullah Bin Zubair(عبد الله بن زبير) wanted to take advantage
and rebuild Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) on the original foundations which he did.
And he fulfilled the description that was given by Rasool Allah ﷺ in the Hadith(حديث),
that he would lower the gate and have an East door and a Western door
and expand the size of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) towards Al-Hijr(الحجر), which he did.
So, that's the third time Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) was rebuilt,
Abdullah Bin Zubair(عبدالله بن زبير) ended up losing the war and he was killed,
Al-Hajjaj Bin Yousuf(الحجاج بن يوسف) took over.
The Khalifah(خليفه) of that time Abdul-Malik Bin Marwaan(عبدالملك بن مروان) was not familiar with this Hadith(حديث).
So, he gave his commands to take back Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) to the way it was before Abdullah Bin Zubair(عبدالله بن زبير).
So, Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) was shortened again, according to the way that people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) built it.
After the Khilafah(خلافة) of Bannu Umayyah(بنو امية),
Bannu Abbas(بنوعباس) were the family of Khulafah(خلافاء).
One of the Khulafah(خلافاء) of Bannu Abbas(بنوعباس) was thinking about rebuilding Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) again,
on the original foundations, and he consulted Al-Imam Malik(الامام مالك),
Imam Malik(امام مالك) told the Khalifah(خليفه) and he gave him a very wise answer.
He said: We don't want Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) to be a toy in the hands of kings.
They keep changing its size every now and then,
even though the plan of Rasool Allah ﷺ and his desire was to build it on the foundations of Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم),
but let's keep it the way it is and not change it anymore.
Because it was going back and forth on the foundations of Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم)
and then the way Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) built it and then again on the foundations of Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم).
Imam Malik(امام مالك) said that,
the people have known Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) and they have known these stones the way they are,
don't keep on changing it, keep it the way it is.
And that was a very wise advice from Al-Imam Malik(الامام مالك) which the Khalifah(خليفه) followed.
So, the Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) that we have today is built on which foundation,
the foundation of Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) or the foundations of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)?
Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
But Al-Hamdolillah(الحمدلله) that's something good.
Why.?
If Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) was built on the original foundations of Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم),
we would have been deprived the chance of praying inside Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
But since it is shortened.
That area which is enclosedby the semi circle is actually part of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
So, when you pray in that area, it is as if you have prayed inside Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
And we know that Rasool Allah ﷺ did pray inside Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
When he opened Makkah, he prayed inside Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه),
he prayed eight Rak'ah(ركعة) inside Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
So, now we have a chance to pray in Al-Hijr(الحجر).
Otherwise, we would have to get permission to get inside Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه)
and it would be very cumbersome and difficult.
But now we can pray inside Al-Hijr(الحجر) and it will count as if you prayed in Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
Now over the time, the height of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) has increased, but the size of it has remained constant.
Now, with the stones that Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه), are built from,
many of them are remnants of the original stones that were used by Ibrahim عليه السّلام,
but not all of them. Some other ones were introduced later by Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) and others.
But the black stone is the original stone that was used by Ibrahim عليه السّلام.
The black stone has never changed, it is the original stone that was given to Ibrahim عليه السّلام.
And there are many stories about the black stone itself.
Some say it originated from Jannah(جنة), there's a Hadith(حديث) that is authentic that says that
the black stone was white, but then it turned black because of the sins of the sons of Adam(آدم).
And there is a Hadith(حديث) that says that the black stone is right hand of Allah on Earth.
So, the black stone is very special, it's very honored,
and it's very respected and it's the only part of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) that is kissed
and is only part of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) that is pointed to from a distance.
Some people they point to the Yemeni corner which is wrong
and Yemeni corner you can touch it when you're passing by it.
But one should not point towards it, or greet it from a distance that is only for the black stone.
So, this is the history of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
The Prophet ﷺ would go out of Makkah and spend time in the cave of Hira(حرا)
in a mountain that is fairly close to Makkah a few kilometers away from Makkah.
Rasool Allah ﷺ will take with him provisions, some food
and he would go and stay in seclusion, solitude in this cave, worshiping Allah سبحانه وتعالى,
and from the cave it is said that you are able to see Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه), in those old days.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ would spend days and nights continuously in the cave, worshipping Allah سبحانه وتعالى before Prophet hood.
So, he knew Allah سبحانه وتعالى and he was worshipping Allah سبحانه وتعالى in that cave.
And this was a chance for Rasool Allah ﷺ to do reflectionand contemplation in the creation of Allah.
And this was training for him Allahسبحانه وتعالى was training him
through these moments of reflection and contemplation, because they purify the heart.
And Saeed Hawwa(سعيد هوّا), he comments on this, he says:
Solitude was the tradition of some, who seek the guidance of Allah, with the remembrance of Allah and worship.
It was used to illuminate the hearts and remove its Shadows by disconnecting it from its heedlessness and desires.
Some would advise this in the beginning of the journey to belief,
as this was the example of the Prophet ﷺ,
when he spent time in solitude before and at the beginning of his apostleship.
So, as a Muslim, you are recommended to spend time alone in Zikr(زكر),
for example, early in the morning, after Asr(عصر), between Asr(عصر) and Maghrib(مغرب) on Friday.
So, you spend time alone remembering Allah in solitude.
And our scholars talked about the benefit of solitude.
Now, one should not go into the extremes of leaving the society completely,
or immersing oneself in the society completely, it should have a middle road.
So, you spend some time with people socializing,
but you also spend time alone between you and Allah.
Qiyaam Ul Lail(قيام اليل) is a chance for solitude,
praying at night alone when everybody's asleep.
So, it's something between you and Allah, there's an element of sincerity there,
that might not exist with other Ibadaat(عبادات) that are done collectively.
So now, you are doing this alone, nobody can see you, you are not showing off,
who are you doing it for?
You are doing it for Allah.
So, it's very important for one, to spend this time in solitude to purify the heart.
Because the scholars say that too much socialization, too much laughing,
too much attachment to Duniyah(دُنِيَّا), obscures the heart and throws veils on it.
And the way to purify the heart is by spending some time worshipping Allah سبحانه وتعالى in solitude.
And Allah سبحانه وتعالى says about Taffakkur(تفكر):
إِنَّ فِي خَلْقِ السَّمَاوَاتِ وَالْأَرْضِ وَاخْتِلَافِ اللَّيْلِ وَالنَّهَارِ لَآيَاتٍ لِأُولِي الْأَلْبَابِ۝
الَّذِينَ يَذْكُرُونَ اللَّهَ قِيَامًا وَقُعُودًا وَعَلَىٰ جُنُوبِهِمْ
وَعَلَىٰ جُنُوبِهِمْ وَيَتَفَكَّرُونَ فِي خَلْقِ السَّمَاوَاتِ وَالْأَرْضِ
رَبَّنَا مَا خَلَقْتَ هَٰذَا بَاطِلًا سُبْحَانَكَ فَقِنَا عَذَابَ النَّارِ۝
Behold, in the creation of the heavens and the earth, and the alternation of night and day,
there are indeed signs for men of understanding.
Men who celebrate the praises of Allah standing, sitting and laying down or lying down on their sides,
and contemplate the wonders of creation in the heavens and the earth with the thought,
Our Lord, not for not has though created all this.
Glory to You, give us salvation from the chastisement of the fire.
So, Allah سبحانه وتعالى is saying here that His servants
contemplate in the creation of the heavens and earth.
And they say: O Allah no, You have not created this in vain.
There's purpose in creation, there's wisdom in everything that exist.
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرًا